Gray, Lois, Collection of Training Materials /4352
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Lois Gray Collection of Training Materials
1948-2016
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Gray, Lois S. (Lois Spier), 1923-2018
New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations
/4352
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
.
10003288
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 18, 2017
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 04, 2019
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Arrangement
Series I: Time Management and Creativity
Series II: Public Speaking
Series III: Meetings and Priorities
Series IV: Public View of Unions
Series V: Motivation and Participation
Series VI: Conflict Resolution and Communication
Series VII: Leadership and Decision Making
Series VIII: Union Democracy and Administration
Biographical / Historical
Lois Gray (October 17, 1923 - September 20, 2018) was the Jean McKelvey-Alice Grant Professor Emeritus and former Dean of Extension of the School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University.
Gray was born in St. Louis, Missouri, and spent her childhood in Edmond, Oklahoma, where she completed high school. She received her bachelor's degree at Park College in Missouri, majoring in Economics.
In 1946, Gray founded the school's first off-campus extension office in Buffalo, and subsequently moving to direct the New York City office in 1956 before being appointed Associate Dean and Director of Extension in 1976. Gray completed graduate degrees (M.A. at University of Buffalo and Ph.D. in Economics from Columbia University) while working fulltime for Cornell ILR.
Many innovative programs were established under her leadership including Labor and Urban Affairs, Programs for Employment and Workplace Systems, the Institute for Women and Work, Summer Schools for Women Union Activists, Hispanic Labor Leadership and Labor Studies for College Credit. As one of the founders of the field of labor education, Gray continued to be both a scholar and labor educator throughout her career. Subjects of her research and publishing included labor market trends, women and minorities in the workforce, training and adult education, labor-management relations in the entertainment industry, and women in union leadership. Another focus of her work was union structure, governance, and administration. In addition, Gray played a role in burgeoning Latin American labor education programs, including those of Chile, Jamaica, Barbados, and Puerto Rico.
Gray received numerous awards over her career, including Lifetime Achievement from the Labor and Employment Relations Association (LERA) and the United Association for Labor Education (UALE). In 2006, she received an award from the Working Theatre for "Bridging the Gap between Arts, Labor and Community." She was appointed by three governors to chair the New York State Apprenticeship and Training Council and served on the New York State Manpower Training Council and Displaced Homemakers Taskforce.
She was an Associate of the Worker Institute where she engaged in research on the arts and entertainment industry. She served in this role at the Worker Institute until she passed. Gray was married to Ed Gray, who had been the Regional Director and Member of the International Executive Board of the UAW.
10003288
- Series I: Time Management and Creativity
  - Time Management (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Time Saving Tips Worksheet (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Creativity Tips from 5 World Famous Artists (email), 2013 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Things to Accomplish Today (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Public Speaking
  - UALE Summer Institute for Union Women Public Speaking Workshop, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - UALE NE Summer School, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series III: Meetings and Priorities
  - Lets Look at a Streamlined Agenda Worksheet (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Special Report: Pinpointing Priorities, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Local Union Meeting by George Strauss and Leonard Sayles, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Guide for Better Union Committees (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Checklist for Union Meetings (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Meeting Design Exercise (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Exercise in Putting a New Idea into Action (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sample Goals and To-Do Lists (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Action Plan Worksheet (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Better Union Meetings Packet (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Effective Meetings (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series IV: Public View of Unions
  - How American Workers View Labor Unions, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Labor Unions in the Public Mind by Seymour Martin Lipset, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series V: Motivation and Participation
  - Motivating (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Local Union Participation: A Re-examination by John C. Anderson, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Revisiting the Relationship Between Union Commitment and Union Participation by Clive J Fullagar, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Building Leadership Skills: What is Empowerment?, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 3 Traits of Cultures that Motivate by Samuel Bacharach (email), 2013 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Worksheet on Participation in the Local Union (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ten Tips on Getting People Involved (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Attitudinal and Behavioral Variables Related to Participation in Union Activities by Gregory E Huszczo, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Building Union Commitment Among New Members: The Role of Formal and Informal Socialization by Paul F Clark, Clive Fullagar, Daniel G Gallagher and Michael E Gordon, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Some Conclusions on Groups (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Steward Update: The Power of Questions, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Involve Members and Advice Of Union Leaders (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Members Wants (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Group IQ: What makes one team of people smarter than another? A new field of research finds surprising answers (email), 2010 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - SEIU: Who Broke the Economy (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Series VI: Conflict Resolution and Communication
  - Communications (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Deep Listening: Listening Habits (email), 2013 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Keeping the Mind Focused (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Union Strategies for Organizing and Representing the New Service Workforce by Dorothy Sue Cobble, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - The Changing Situation of Workers and Their Unions (AFL-CIO Report), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Developing an Agenda: Expanding the Role of Women in Unions by Naomi Baden, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Conflicts within the Local Union by Leonard R Sayles and George Strauss, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Some Problems of Communication in the Local Union by Leonard R Sayles and George Strauss, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Life Styles Inventory LSI Conflict Self-Development Guide by Human Synergistics International, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Strategic Communication Worksheet (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - 1199 SEIU Training at Cornell ILR, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Choosing Issues: Seven Goals (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Setting Clear Goals and Expectations (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Diversity and Inclusion in Unions Case Study, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Listening Skills (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Workshop Goal: To Develop a New Way Of: Looking At Thinking About Performing the Role of Listening (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Barriers to Effective Communications Across Cultures (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Causes of Divisiveness Packet, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Conflict Resolution (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Series VII: Leadership and Decision Making
  - What Makes a Leader? By Daniel Goleman, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Building Leadership Skills: 50 Phrases that Block Improvement, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Coaching, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - The Next Generation: A Handbook for Mentoring Future Union Leaders (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Leadership Development (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Recommended Teaching Outline for Leadership Skills Curriculum, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - A Strategic Choice Framework for Union Decision Making by David Weil, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Pragmatic Leadership, Samuel Bacharach (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Management Skills for Union Leaders Questionnaire (email), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Leadership Within Unions Cornell University, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Leadership in Unions Cornell University, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Managing with Union Values Leadership Class Schedule, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Union Leadership Workshop on Supervision in Unions (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Outline: Management and Leadership in Unions (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Tasks Performed by Leaders from John W Gardners Leadership Papers, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Management vs Leadership (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Managers and Leaders: Are They Different? by Abraham Zaleznik, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Types of Leadership Transactional Transformational (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Leading Organizational Change (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Situational Leadership Packet, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Building Leadership Skills: Situational Leadership Model Packet (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Situational Leadership Adjusting Leadership Style to Follower Readiness (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Union Presidents Views of their Role as Managers (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - The Dysfunctional Union Manager Case Study (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - The Ideal Union Manager Case Study (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Leadership Scenarios (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - The New People of Power: The Backgrounds and Careers of Top Labor Leaders by Philip L Quaglier, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Black Union Leaders at the Local Level by Roger Lamm, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - The Changing of the Guard: The New American Labor Leader b Arthur R Schwartz and Michele M Hoyman, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - The Managers Job Folklore and Fact by Henry Mintzberg, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - The Unpaid Local Leader by George Strauss and Leonard Sayles, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Ideal Leader Behavior Questionnaire (What you expect of a Leader) (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Locating Scores on the Ohio State Leadership Studies Model (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Making a Difference Through Leadership and Power, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Leadership Style: Scoring Key for Initiating Structure (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Leadership Inventory: Behaviors, Qualities and Skills of Effective Union Leaders, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Empowering Members Through Your Leadership Style: Whats your ELQ? (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Your Working/Leadership Style (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Leadership Values to Transform Unions by Gene Caroll, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Leadership and Organizational Transformation (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - A Model of Effective Union Leadership (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - The Nature of Leadership: Introductory Considerations by John W. Gardner, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Leadership Theories Packet (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Leadership Without Presumption: Lessons From Eisenhower by Samuel Bacharach, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Union Leadership Packet, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - 1199 Organizers Training Packet: Communication Strategies for Union Leaders, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Leadership in Unions Packet, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Power, Authority, and Leadership Styles in Unions (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - AFT Qualities of Admired Leaders (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Timed Agenda: Women's Leadership Caf (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Tips for Women Achieving Power and Leadership in their Unions, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Class Notes on Women as Union Leaders, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Why Women Still Can't Have It All, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Do you want to communicate well ad be more persuasive? Then Listen up! Handout (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Outline for Leadership Skills Agenda Packet (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Shut up and Sit Down; Why the Leadership Industry Rules by Joshua Rothman NYT, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - Strategic Transformation; How the best companies for Leadership excel at both innovation and operational excellence by HeyGroup, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Leadership Lessons From a Dysfunctional Congress by Samuel Bacharach (email), 2013 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Jeff Bezos Innovation Formula by Samuel Bacharach (email), 2013 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Planning (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Strategic Planning for Seasoned Leaders Steps Packet (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Leadership Within Unions Course Syllabus, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Portside Labor: Have we Built the Committee by Seth Newton Patel, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Inclusive Leadership: The View from 6 countries (email), 2014 (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - What Leaders Really Do by John P Kotter, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Influencing Attitudes and Behaviors to Promote Your Cause by National Prevention Science Coalition to Improve Lives (email), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - Appreciative Leadership Profile Template (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - Gender and the Emergence of Leaders: A Meta-Analysis by Alice H Eagly and Steven J Karau, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 121)
  - Problem Solving Techniques (Box 1, Folder 122)
- Series VIII: Union Democracy and Administration
  - Union Government and Organization by James Wallihan, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Strategic Issues in Finance and Resource Allocation Article, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Teamsters Guide to Local Union Administration; Teamsters Education Department (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - National Union Administration Conference by George Meany Center for Labor Studies, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Union Government in the US: Research Past and Future by George Strauss (booklet), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mechanisms of Control in Local Trade Unions by Arnold Tannenbaum, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dual Government in Unions: A Tool for Analysis by Alice H Cook, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - A Glossary of Labor Terms (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Union Administrative Practices: A Comparative Analysis from the Journal of Labor Research Winter 1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Executives in Four Fields by John Dunlop, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Constitution and By-Laws Exercise (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Trends in Union Organizing Issues and Tactics by Monty L Lynn and Jozell Brister, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Constitutional Power of the Chief Officer in American Labor Unions, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Part III Democratic Practices: Reality and Model (Book) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Fight for Union Democracy by Herman Benson (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Effect of the LMRDA Upon Union Constitutions by Philip Ross and Philip Taft, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Management of Human Resource in National Unions by Paul F Clark, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Union Administration by Paul F Clark and Lois S Gray, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The Election Base of National Union Executive Boards by Sara Gamm, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - A Comparison of Executives in Four Fields by John T Dunlop, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Appendix A Merger Guidelines (Membership Tables) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Union Administration Chapter for the State of Unions by George Strauss, Daniel G Gallagher and Jack Fiorito, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Finances of American Unions in the 1970s by Neil Sheflin and Leo Troy, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Cornell University Trade Union Womens Studies Manual on Union Organizing and Administration by Barbara M Wertheimer, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Special Report: Union Administration Assessment by Union Labor Report, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The Governments RICO Suit Against the Teamsters; A Statement by the Association for Union Democracy, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Union Democracy in the International Typographical Union: Thirty Years Later by Kay Stratton, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Readings on Union Government and Administration by Professor Lois Gray, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Part III Democratic Practices: Reality and Model (Book) Chapter 7 An Evaluation of Democratic Practices (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Unions and Legitimacy: A Conceptual Refinement by Gary N Chaison, Barbara Bigelow and Edward Ottensmeyer, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Trade Union Administration by Professor John T Dunlop (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Industrial and Labor Relations Review: Shop Society and the Union, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - American Unions Structure, Government and Politics by Jack Barbash Chapter III The Local Union, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Areas of Worker Decision Making; Workers Decisions and Production (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Readings on Union Government Labor Studies L270 IUPUI by Jim Wallihan, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Conference Board Reports; Handbook of Union Government Structure and Procedures, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Union Democracy: Practice and Ideal An Analysis of Four Large Local Unions by Alice H Cook, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Labor Economics and Labor Relations by Lloyd G Reynolds 6th Edition, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Class Notes: Union Structure and Government (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Questions for Study in Term Paper on a Selected Union (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Issues in Union Structure by George Strauss, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - The Historical Role of American Trade Unionism by Walter Galenson (summary) (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - The Gompers Rule: Autonomy (Newspaper clipping), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - The Rise of Industrial Unionism by Jack Barbash, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - The Union as an Evolving Organization by Jack Barbash, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Industrial Relation Research Institute; Rationalization in the American Union by Jack Barbash, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Union Adaptation to Changes in the Labor Force by Joel Seidman (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Towards and Organizational Study of Trade Unions by John Child, Ray Loveridge and Malcolm Warner, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Unions, Bureaucracy, and Change: Old Dogs Learn New Tricks Very Slowly by James A Craft, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Union Government in the US: Research Past and Future by George Strauss, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - New Forms of Human Organizations by Charles C Heckscher, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Two Frames of Unionism (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Worker Rights: An Emerging Paradigm? By Jonathan Kranz, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Legal Rights of Union Members (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Structural Changes in the American Labor Movement and Industrial Relations System John T Dunlop, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - The Practice of Unionism, Union Structure and Government by Jack Barbash, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Structure: Union Research Agenda for the 1990s by George Strauss, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Union Structure and Administration; Union Information Questionnaire (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Union Democracy in the Construction Trades (booklet), 1985 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Union Democracy and Landrum-Griffin by Clyde W Summers, Joseph L Rauh and Herman Benson, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - A Comparative Analysis of Local Union Democracy by John C Anderson, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - The Labor Sector; An Introduction to Labor in the American Economy by Neil W Chamberlain, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Local Union Dimensions (outline/ class notes?) (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Wallihan Chapter 5; Workplace and Local Union Organization (Summary/ Outline) (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Questions about Union Democracy (class notes) (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - The Fight for Union Democracy by Herman Benson (class notes) (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Democracy, Union Government and the Interests of the Members, Chapter 3 Bok and Dunlop (outline) (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Questions for Discussion; Local Union Democracy (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Special Report: Democracy at the Local Level, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - George Brooks Rank and File Notes (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Questions for Discussion on Sources of Vitality for the American Labor Movement (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Union Structure and Government (Class Notes) (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Chapter 1; Studies and Views of Democracy in Unions, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Landrum Griffin by Susan Jennick (Class Notes) (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Questions about Landrum-Griffin (class notes and questions) (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Labor Management Reporting and Disclosure Act (LMRD) Class Notes (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Questions on Local Unions (Class Notes) (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Class Notes on John C Anderson (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - LIR 411 Clark (Readings on Unions for Spring Semester 1991) (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - AFL-CIO Department of Education Building the Local Union (Booklet) (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Union Administration Material (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Building Your Caucus with the Member to Member Network (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Running for Local Union Office (Box 2, Folder 83)